A Finding Aid to the Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer Family Papers, 1851-1999 (bulk 1881-1950), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1867-1987; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer Correspondence, 1881-1921; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Sa-Sl, 1896-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Sainsbury, Harrington
      Sears, Sara C.
      Secretary of the Admiralty
      Shelden, C. S.
      Shurtleff, Roswell Morse
      Shurtleff, William H.
      Slack, Julia L.
      Sloane, William M.
    - Sm-St, 1899-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Smith, William Lord
      Southwick, E. B.
      Stephens, T. C.
      Stillman, Clara
    - Taber, E. M. & Frances F. Holt (Taber's sister), 1890-1896; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Taber, E. M. & Frances F. Holt (Taber's sister), 1901-1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Taber, E. M. & Frances F. Holt (Taber's sister), 1911-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Thayer, Emma Beach, 1881-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Thayer, Emma Beach, 1890-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Thayer, Emma Beach, Undated Letters, circa 1881-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - T-V, 1890, 1907-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
      Thayer, David
      Thayer, Gerald
      Tiffany, Louis Comfort
      Tryon, Dwight W.
      Van Norden, Ottomar H.
      Von Wittenburg, Marie
    - War Office, London, 1916-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1904-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Wa-We, 1896-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
      Walker, H. O.
      Wallace, Alfred R.
      Walton, Blanche W.
      Warren, Gretchen
      Watkins & Doncaster
      Webster, Arthur Gordon
      Weigels, Mrs.
      Weld, George F.
      Wellesley College
      Wentworth, N.
    - Wh-Wy, 1882-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
      White, Stanford
      Wilcox, W. D.
      Wild Life Protection League of America
      Wilson, Woodrow
      Wyeth, N. C.
      Wylie, J. E.
    - Y-Z, 1889, 1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Yale University
      Zuler?, H. Morris
    - Unidentified Correspondents, 1891-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Unidentified Correspondents, Fragments, circa 1880-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Emma Beach Thayer Correspondence, 1865-1924; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries contains the correspondence of Emma Beach Thayer, also known as Addie by her family, and document her personal life, family relationships, and management of Abbott Thayer's legacy. Found here is a large amount of correspondence with family members, including her step-daughters Mary and Gladys, her step-son Gerald, as well as her parents, sisters, nephews, nieces, and other extended family. Also found is extensive correspondence with her friend, and Thayer's first wife, Kate Bloede Thayer. Much of her correspondence is with the same people who corresponded with Abbott Thayer, but also includes other friends, most notably, Henry Ward Beecher.
    After 1916 Emma managed much of Abbott Thayer's correspondence due to his poor health, and included here are a few letters regarding the sale or exhibition of his artwork. Many of the letters found here are condolences to Emma after Abbott's death in 1921, including many letters from artists and friends expressing thoughts and memories of his life. There are also letters from Emma to many of Abbott's friends requesting his letters or copies of his for a planned book of Thayer's correspondence.
    Researchers should note that correspondence between Emma and Abbott is arranged in subseries 2.1. Emma's correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name and chronologically within each folder.
    - A, 1905, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 77)
      Addams, Jane
      Allen, Glover M.
      Allen, Irene C.
      Allen, Nellie Wright
      American Federation of Arts
      Andrews, Robert D.
      Atlantic Monthly
      Ayres, Philip W.
    - Beach, Moses S. & Chloe (parents), 1865-1866, 1870, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Beach, William & Mabel, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward, undated, 1870; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward, 1875-1883; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Benson, Frank W., 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, undated, 1891-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1922 February-April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1922 May-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1922 August-September; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1922 October-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Ba-Bi, 1878, 1914-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 90)
      Backhouse, Irene
      Barker, Virgil
      Bartsch, Paul
      Bayard, Mabel
      Beach, Ella
      Beatty, Mr.
      Beaulieu, Bessie Price
      Bigelow, Henry B.
    - Bl-Bu, 1917-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 91)
      Bowditch, Nancy
      Bowditch, Vincent Y.
      Brackett, Mary A.
      Bradley, Susan H.
      Brown, Demetra & Kenneth
      Browne, George & Emily H.
      Brush, George de Forest
    - Clemens, Samuel, circa 1880s, 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Cortissoz, Royal, 1917, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - C, 1917-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 94)
      Carr, W. S.
      Churchill, Alfred
      Coffin, Grace P.
      Cole, Kate Foote
      Cole, Timothy
      Curtis, Benjamin
    - Dow, Thomas Millie, 1884-1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - D-E, circa 1900-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 96)
      Dewing, Maria Oakey
      Dickerson, Roy E.
      Dow, Florence E.
      Elliot, Mary
      Emerson, Annie S.
      Emerson, Edward W.
    - Freer, Charles L., 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - French, Daniel Chester, 1917-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - F, 1907-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 100)
      Field, Mary D.
      Forbes, Alexander
      Foster, Ben
      Freer Gallery of Art
      Fuller, Lucie Fairchild
    - Gellatly, John, 1917-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Gellatly, John, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Gellatly, John, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - G, 1920-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Gab__?, Clara C.
      Gould, Laura Stedman
      Goodnow, W. L.
      Gulick, Alida Carey
    - H, 1916-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Hassam, Childe
      Hawthorne, Marion
      Historical Press Association
      Holt, Florence F.
      Houghton Mifflin Company
    - James, William & Alice, 1921-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - J-L, 1906-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Jenkins, Elizabeth F.
      John Lane Company
      Kent, Rockwell
      Keyes, Alicia
      Kittredge, S. Dana
      Low, Will H.
    - M, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Macbeth, Robert W.
      MacKaye, Percy
      Masefield, J.
      Mason, John?
      McIlvane, William M.
      Merriman, Charlotte B.
      Morris, Harrison S.
    - N-P, 1918-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
      National Association of Audubon Societies
      Of, George Ferdinand
      Pabrelivitsch?, Mme. Ossip
      Pevey?, Eustace
      Powell, Caroline
      Powers, Henrietta
      Putnam, James J.
    - Reasoner, David, 1920-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1910-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1917-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1919-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, Undated Letters, circa 1910-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Rice, James Henry, 1921-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - R-S, 1913-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Reilly, Mary S.
      Roosevelt, Edith K.
      Sainsbury, Grace E.
      Sargent, John Singer
      Sears, Mrs.
      Sharman, John
      Shurtleff, Clara E.
      Slack, Julia
      Smart, Ann Wentworth
      Smith, Annie Morrill
      Smith, H. A. Hammond
      Stillman, Evangeline
      Stone, Ellen J.
    - Thayer, Gerald H., 1917, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Thayer, Gerald H., 1922-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, 1881; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, 1882; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, 1883; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, 1884-1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, Undated Letters, circa 1881-circa 1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Thayer, Kate Bloede, Undated Letters, circa 1881-circa 1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - T-V, 1891, 1908-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Thayer, Dr. William & Ellen Handerson
      Treasury Department, Internal Revenue Service
      Troccoli, Giovanni B.
      Twitchill?, Charlotte H. P.
      Van Loon, Elize Bowditch
      Von Villern, Wilhelmina
      Vose, Robert C.
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1905-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1916-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1922-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, Undated Letters, circa 1905-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - W-Y, 1916-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Walker, Henry O.
      War Office, London
      Wheeler, Emma H.
      White, Lawrence Grant
      Whiting, Sue Thayer
      Whiting, Winifred Harris
      Whitney, Douglas
      Wister, Owen
      Wyeth, Annie W.
    - Unidentified Correspondents, 1867-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Kate Bloede Thayer Correspondence, 1881-1889; 2.3; Archival Resource Key
    Kate Bloede Thayer's correspondence documents family activities and friendships during the 1880s. Included are letters in German from her grandfather, letters from her brother, Victor, and several letters from her daughter Mary sent during Kate's time at a sanatorium. Also found are letters from artist friends including Arthur Bell, Thomas Millie Dow, and Lewis T. Ives. Dow's letters discuss his travels in Europe, his current artwork, mutual friends such as Arthur Bell, and other general news. Ives's letters also discuss mutual friends and general news. Letters from Kate to her in-laws, William and Ellen Thayer, discuss family news and news of Abbot's work. Other correspondence, arranged alphabetically, contains letters from family and friends. Correspondence between Kate Bloede Thayer and Emma Beach Thayer is found with Emma Beach's correspondence.
    - Bloede, Grandpa, 1881-1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Bloede, Victor, 1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1888-1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Dow, Thomas Millie, 1881-1886; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Ives, Lew. T., 1882-1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Thayer, Dr. William & Ellen Handerson, 1881; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Thayer, Dr. William & Ellen Handerson, 1883; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Thayer, Dr. William & Ellen Handerson, 1884-1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - B-H, 1882-1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - M-S, 1887-1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified letter fragments, 1880s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Gladys Thayer Reasoner Correspondence, 1907-1943; 2.4; Archival Resource Key
    The correspondence of Gladys Thayer Reasoner, a.k.a Galla, documents family activities and her friendships. Found here are letters to and from family members, including her sister Mary, her brother Gerald (known as Gra), nephews, nieces, and other extended family, such as her cousins in the Foster and Whiting families. Additional letters are from friends, including Randolph Bourne, Frances Burns, Evangeline Stillman, Blanche Walton, and others. Gladys also maintained correspondence with Thayer family friends, who were friends of her parents, or members of the Dublin, New Hampshire community in which they lived, such as Mary Amory Greene, John Gellatly, Richard Meryman, Raphael Pumpelly, and Jay and Philip Whelpley. Gladys' correspondence is also found in the subseries containing her father and stepmother Emma Beach Thayer correspondence.
    - Birch, Elsie, 1916-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1916-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Bourne, Randolph, 1915-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Buckley, Lily, 1917-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Burns, Frances L., circa 1920-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - B, 1912-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
      Beach, Violet
      Beaulieu, Mary
      Berlingham, Robert
      Buckley, Lou
    - C-D, 1907-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Cameron, Hugh A.
      Clemens, Jean
      Comstock, Charlie L.
      Cortissoz, Royal
      Daniels, George E.
    - Fisher, Eleanor, 1908-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Fisher, Faith H. (Mrs. William F. Fenn), 1928-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Fisher, Richard & Nina, 1939-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - F, 1911-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 57)
      F., W. W.
      Fisher, Ellen Thayer
    - G-H, 1909-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Gellatly, John
      Gleason, John R.
      Goldschmidt, Anita
      Harvard College, Museum of Comparative Zoology
      Hoen, A. B.
      Hu_?, Evan
    - J, 1911-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 59)
      James, Henry
      James, Nina Marion
      James, William
    - K-L, 1908-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Keane, Polla Price
      Kellogg, Foster S.
      Kittredge, Anna M.
      Kleb, Sarah M.
      Lord, Ruth Whiting
      Lowder, Isabel
    - M-O, 1922-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 61)
      MacVeagh, Eames
      Martin, Polly (Mrs. G. Rainsford Martin)
      Meryman, Richard S. (Wig)
      Nautilus Beach Club
      Ohta family
    - Palmer, H. P., 1935-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - P, 1911-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Page, Arthur W.
      Paramount Pictures Distributing Corporation
      Percy, Eustace
      Pinkham, M.
      Public Works of Art Project
      Pumpelly, Raphael
      Putnam, Shirley
    - Reasoner, David, 1921-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - R, 1922-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Reasoner, Mrs. (David's Mother)
      Reasoner, Nan
      Rodakiewicz, Eva
    - Stillman, Michael & Evangeline, 1909-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - S, 1911, 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 67)
      Schurmeier, Theodora
      Stokes, Rose Paxton
    - Thayer, Gerald H., 1908-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - T, 1911-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Tax Commissioner
      Thayer, Alma
      Thayer, Bernie
      Tish, Hay
      Treasury Department, Public Works of Art Project
    - Walton, Blanche W., 1923-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, undated, 1907-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1925-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1932-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1936-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Whiting, Susan Thayer, 1928-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - W, 1912-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 76)
      W., Marion W.
      Wangler, Kathy & Albert McCreery
      War Department
      Warner, Langdon
      White, Nelson C.
      Whiting, Rose
      The Woman Citizen
      Wynne, Annette
    - First Names Only: A-H, 1912-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - First Names Only: J-R, 1907-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - David Reasoner Correspondence, 1918-1954; 2.5; Archival Resource Key
    David Reasoner's correspondence is primarily with family and friends, such as Emma Beach Thayer's sister, Violet, and from Mary Thayer Birch discussing Emma's estate, Gerald's ill health, and other family news. David Reasoner also corresponded with John Gellatly concerning the sale of Abbott Thayer's paintings, and with Gerald Thayer concerning financial matters. Other alphabetical correspondence is with Thayer and Reasoner family members, people working on books or requesting information on Abbott Thayer, museums exhibiting Thayer's work, and people interested in purchasing artwork by Thayer. Also found are letters concerning the deaths of Reasoner's mother, his wife Gladys, and his son Allen. The bulk of the David Reasoner correspondence concerning the estates of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma Beach Thayer is found in Series 4: Estate Papers.
    - Beach, Violet, 1924-1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Birch, Mary Thayer, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Gellatly, John, 1924-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Thayer, Gerald, 1922-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - A-B, 1921-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - C-D, 1925, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - F-G, 1924-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - H-J, 1925-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - L-P, 1922-1936, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - R, 1924-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - T-V, 1918, 1943-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - W, 1928-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified Correspondents, 1942-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1883-1987; 2.6; Archival Resource Key
    This series contains the correspondence of other members of the Thayer and Reasoner families. Included is correspondence between Elsie Birch and her cousins, and the correspondence of her mother, Mary Thayer Birch. Also found are letters to Jean Reasoner Plunket, Abbott Thayer's granddaughter, including many from Nelson C. White, who collected research material for a biography of Abbott Thayer.
    Gerald H. Thayer's correspondence discusses concealing coloration, the estate of Abbott and Emma Thayer, and letters of condolence from George Gray Barnard and Edwin H. Blashfield. Additional correspondence found here includes letters to Gerald's wife, Alma, from the family friend and Thayer patron, John Gellatly, letters to Abbott Thayer's parents, Dr. William and Ellen Thayer, and letters to Jay and Philip Whelpley, family friends of the Thayers.
    - Elsie Birch, 1933, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Mary Thayer Birch, 1886-1915, circa 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jean Reasoner Plunket, 1945-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Allen Reasoner, 1935-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Alma E. Thayer from John Gellatly, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Gerald H. Thayer, 1908-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Dr. William H. Thayer and Ellen Handerson Thayer, 1883-1891; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Jay and Philip Whelpley, 1910-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1908-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Writings, 1888-1945; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 3-4; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series contains writings by Abbott Handerson Thayer and others, including family members and scholars. Writings by Thayer primarily focus on his theories about concealing coloration and nature observations through notes and draft writings. Also found are his writings on other topics such as the restoration of artwork. Writings by others include the writings of Emma Beach Thayer and Abbott Thayer's daughters Mary and Gladys, and writings by scholars about the Thayer's artwork.
  The Writings series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Writings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, circa 1890-1918
  Subseries 3.2: Writings by Others, 1888-1989
  - Writings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, circa 1890-1918; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    Writings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, primarily on the topic of concealing coloration and his observations of nature, include four small notebooks. His notes and draft essays, often written on small scraps of paper or the back of other documents, are on the topic of concealing coloration in nature, and the related topics, the invisibility of icebergs and the concealing coloration in military uniforms and warships. Many of his notes appear to be preparations for lectures or letters to the editor on these topics, or responses to the negative feedback from his book Concealing Coloration in Nature, published in 1909. Also found are draft essays on the restoration of works of art and notes and essays on various subjects such as the Boer war, art, and other thoughts on nature.
    - Notebooks, circa 1890-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Notebooks, circa 1890-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Nature, circa 1910-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Nature, circa 1910-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Nature, circa 1910-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Nature, circa 1910-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Notes & Essays on the Invisibility of Icebergs, 1912; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)